RAJEEV SINGH

639 Washington Avenue Apt. 1, Albany NY 12206 | 518.495.2093 | rajeevsingh03@hotmail.com | LinkedIn in

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Multi-faceted Application and Database Developer with proven experience leading initiatives that add business value through improving the software development processes while continuing to expand functionality and bring application development to the next level. Strong technical background in JAVA, JSP Servlets, SQL Server, MSBI technologies with extensive experience in the full lifecycle of the software design process. Exceptional interpersonal and analytical expertise with a passion for increasing organizational profitability by aligning my knowledge to execute on company goals and application objectives successfully.

TECHNICAL SKILLS	
Operating Systems	Windows, Unix, Linux (RedHat Enterprise Linux, Ubuntu, IBM AIX)
Programming	C\C++, Core Java, JSP Servlets, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Bootstrap, C#, VB, SQL, T-SQL, PL/SQL, React, JavaScript ES8
Database Management	MySQL, SQL Server (SSIS, SSRS, SSAS), Oracle, Teradata, IBM DB2, MongoDB
Tools	Eclipse, Microsoft Visual Studio, Putty, Wireshark, Network miner, DataStage, Tectia
Data Reporting Tools	Tableau, SQL Server Reporting Services, Power BI
Cloud	Amazon Web Services - EC2, S3, Route 53
Version Control	GIT, Subversion
Others	Microsoft Office, SharePoint, Microsoft Project, Apache Tomcat, Junit Testing Framework

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

NYS OFFICE OF INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY SERVICES | Albany, NY

October 2017 - Present

Student Intern-SQL/BI Developer

Build and maintain SQL scripts, indexes, and complex queries for data analysis and extraction; provide database coding to support business applications using C# T-SQL.

- Plan, design, and implement application database code objects, including stored procedures and views.
- Ensure best practices are applied, and integrity of data is maintained through security, documentation, and change management.
- Design and develop ETL processes using SSIS, Multi-Dimensional Data Cube model using SSAS, create reports using SSRS.
- Develop ER Diagrams and Schemas to help the ETL Process Designing.
- Deploy and automate process for Daily Functioning using SQL Server Integration Catalogs.
- Develop Data Warehouses using Kimball methodology; utilize excellent T-SQL development skills to write complex queries.
- Perform SQL query performance tuning by creating/modifying indexes, changing query structures.
- Administer SQL server, manage databases, users, Linked Servers, SQL Server Agent.

UNIVERSITY AT ALBANY Albany, NY

January 2017 - May 2017

Teaching Assistant – Data Structures and Algorithms

- Instructed 40+ students on Data Structures and Algorithms with Java programming.
- Collaborated with a team of TA's to develop assignments and coding challenges for students.
- Met with students during office hours and helped professor to develop course plans.

WIPRO TECHNOLOGIES | Pune, India

January 2014 - June 2016

Project Engineer

Worked on series of customer projects for Vantiv and Citibank. Automated patching of Vantiv servers from manual mode to reduce process time with help of IBM-BigFix tool. Worked on Citibank Genesis program providing solutions to support common pool of contracts, positions, and customer account balances across CITI on an enterprise basis to common data model, including reference data which was based upon Enterprise Data Standards and anchored to financials.

- Ensured and maintained data consistency and data quality for each program part of scheduled production runs.
- Enforced Tectia Client as UNIX platform to run production jobs and checked job level info.
- Used SQL Developer as to create daily tabular reports using complex queries and PL/SQL which was consumed by higher officials.
- Performed SQL query performance tuning by implementing window functions and materialized views.
- Provided 24x7 operational support to all production practices on holidays and weekends.

PROJECTS

UNIVERSITY AT ALBANY | Albany, NY

January 2017 - May 2017

Apartment Management System (https://github.com/rajeevsingh03/Makan/)

MAKAN - Apartment Management System (AMS) is intended to meet requirements of administrator, residents, and visitors of apartments; application stores information about apartment availability, residents, maintenance and other details.

- Developed to provide convenience, ease of access and single point of access to information and other administrative tasks related to apartments.
- Offers users various functionalities which include all possible scenarios which may arise in an apartment. Developed using Java J2EE, jQuery, JavaScript, JSP Ajax, Servlets, JSP, bootstrap, Hibernate, HTML5, CSS3 and MySQL

UNIVERSITY AT ALBANY Albany, NY

January 2017 - May 2017

Employee Management System (https://github.com/rajeevsingh03/Employee-Management-System)

Simple employee management system which handles 3 users: Employee, Manager, and Admin. Every user has distinct functionality. Managers can create directories with Public, Private, Protected and Default Permissions.

- Public directories are visible to all employees in the system. Private directories are visible to current manager and all super managers.
- Default directories are visible to Current Manager Tree (till leaf) and all super managers until it is restricted. Protected directories are visible to Current Manager Tree (till leaf), Another Team Employee (ATE) and all super managers until it is restricted. Developed using JAVA, JSP Servlets, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript and MySQL.

SRM UNIVERSITY | India

January 2013 - May 2013

Ecommerce (https://github.com/rajeevsingh03/Ecommerce)

Online Electric Zone – eCommerce portal developed in JAVA, JSP Servlets, HTML, CSS, JavaScript and Oracle is complete end to end solution to cover all aspects of online buy and sale.

- Provides complete web site solution, including shopping cart, product management, customer management.
- All products are categorized by category of products, and provide powerful product search facilities; search can be done by using product name, product description, location, category.
- Add multiple product to shopping card, automatic calculate the shipping price, and calculate total amount.
- System has transactional data, and all the update and delete operations are recorded for audit purpose.
- System has powerful logical access management in place, each user must be identified by login id and strict password policy.
- Generate various reports for management like, Total Customers by Date/Trend, Customer to Purchase Stats (% of visitors that convert, etc.), Total sale by date.

EDUCATION

Master of Science (MS): Computer Science, University at Albany, State University of New York, Albany, NY, May 2018

Bachelor of Technology: Computer Science, SRM University, Ghaziabad, Uttar Pradesh, India, May 2013

CERTIFICATES

Oracle Certificate Program in Advanced Java Programming for Web Development, January 2014
Oracle Certificate in Java Programming Languages using Java SE6, December 2013
Certificate in Developing Web Applications using ASP.NET, November 2013